<item>
   <title>Issue #554 created</title>
   <pubDate>2023-06-15T01:49:25Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/554</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2023/#created-554</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Transitive Closure function produces an incomplete result, completeness/success and number of actual iterations must also be returned&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;@michaelhkay and CG members,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I initially reopened &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/518"&gt;the original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, because there is some useful and needed functionality that the PR and the text of the FO specification do not provide, and we missed to discuss this at the June 13th meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I believe that typically a developer would need to know if the "whole" TC was completely produced, or not, and maybe how many iterations were needed&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be provided if the result of the function was for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-xq"&gt;map{ 
        "TC" : $thefinalTCNodeset,
        "WasTCComplete": $boolForTCCompletion,
        "NumberOfIterations: $someInteger
       }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One could argue that if &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;$result? NumberOfIterations &amp;lt; max&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, then we know that the complete TC was produced and thus we don't need the member "WasTCComplete".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this is not the case when &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;$result? NumberOfIterations eq max&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In this case both outcomes are possible: the complete TC was produced exactly in &lt;code&gt;max&lt;/code&gt; iterations (so the value of &lt;code&gt;"WasTCComplete"&lt;/code&gt;  must be &lt;code&gt;true()&lt;/code&gt; ), or &lt;code&gt;max&lt;/code&gt; iterations were performed and the &lt;code&gt;max + 1&lt;/code&gt;st iteration produced additional nodes -- in this case &lt;code&gt;"WasTCComplete"&lt;/code&gt; must be &lt;code&gt;false()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Failure to produce the complete TC in many cases will be regarded as error, and the developer needs to be sure that this was (or this wasn't) the case&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;thus, the current specification of this function needs additional work to accomodate the full needed functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
