<item>
   <title>Issue #616 created</title>
   <pubDate>2023-07-18T02:26:33Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/616</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2023/#created-616</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;XDM: X Node vs. x node&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the risk of being branded a pedant....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently the XDM specs have a predilection for Attribute Node, Element Node, Comment Node, Document Node, Text Node, Processing Instruction Node, Namespace Node. But in a healthy minority of cases in the XDM specs, they are rendered lowercase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To complicate matters further, the other specs, which rely upon the XDM specs for the definition of the terms, universally prefer the lowercase form, and they use the terms preponderantly more. A healthy sample of four of the terms across five of the specifications ("elective" excludes instances where that particular case is required, e.g., capitalization in headers):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Term | Spec | Capitalized | Electively Capitalized | Electively Noncapitalized
-- | -- | -- | -- | --
Attribute node | XDM | 71 | 41 | 18
Element node | XDM | 79 | 71 | 23
Comment node | XDM | 44 | 39 | 0
Document node | XDM | 55 | 48 | 10
Attribute node | Serialization | 0 | 0 | 15
Element node | Serialization | 0 | 0 | 39
Comment node | Serialization | 0 | 0 | 2
Document node | Serialization | 0 | 0 | 15
Attribute node | XQuery | 1 | 0 | 82
Element node | XQuery | 0 | 0 | 141
Comment node | XQuery | 0 | 0 | 9
Document node | XQuery | 2 | 0 | 50
Attribute node | XFO | 1 | 0 | 28
Element node | XFO | 1 | 0 | 67
Comment node | XFO | 1 | 0 | 4
Document node | XFO | 1 | 0 | 57
Attribute node | XSLT | 8 | 0 | 100
Element node | XSLT | 16 | 0 | 77
Comment node | XSLT | 1 | 0 | 6
Document node | XSLT | 12 | 0 | 144&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change all specs to capitalize these terms universally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change only XDM to capitalize these terms universally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine a principle that would differentiate the contexts in which the term should be capitalized or not within XDM only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change all specs to uncapitalize these terms universally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal preference is no. 5. I do not see any passages in XDM where the reader would be confused by the term being uncapitalized (the minority cases being witnesses). Lowercase would bring XDM into conformity with the other specifications, and with how the term is commonly used outside the specs. Further, the XDM specs do not capitalize other terms it specially defines, e.g., accessor. And in all the specs, including XDM, the clear preference is to use the lowercase for the names in the raw (i.e., without "node"): element, attribute, namespace, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to bring this to the group before doing any edits. I am happy to do the work, but do not want to do it if it is unwelcome, or if there is a clear preference for another option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
