<item>
   <title>Pull request #797 created</title>
   <pubDate>2023-10-31T03:33:19Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/pull/797</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2023/#created-797</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Edits to parse-uri()&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attn @ndw -- these edits pertain to 6.6.1 &lt;code&gt;fn:parse-uri&lt;/code&gt; and require your careful review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;hierarchical&lt;/code&gt; option appears in the rules of the function but not its preamble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"This function is described..." moved to anticipate the actual narrative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was a bit thrown by the phrase "This approach...is not implementation advice" because "approach" is vague and the reader is left with the impression that a good deal of &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; that follows is non-normative. We offer non-normative prose in the rules, but that informal prose is normally followed by an equivalent description that &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; normative. I did not make any edits in this area, but I would recommend clarification as to exactly what parts of the narrative are normative and which are non-normative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The period-to-colon change at 27573 is to make sure the reader remains aware of the governing "If..." clause.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I deleted a paragraph that attempted to distill the rather complicated description of &lt;code&gt;fn:decode-from-uri&lt;/code&gt;. A mere xref provides a cleaner narrative here and a more accurate description of uri decoding, and the xref is within the same document, so should not pose a burden on the reader.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the &lt;code&gt;query-parameters&lt;/code&gt; there was a discrepancy in the data model presented (in the preamble versus in the function rules), and I opted for the array-of-maps model. If it's supposed to be the other way (simple map), let me know and I'll revise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;query-segments&lt;/code&gt; versus &lt;code&gt;query-parameters&lt;/code&gt;; I went with the latter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know where things ain't right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
