<item>
   <title>Issue #894 created</title>
   <pubDate>2023-12-12T11:21:21Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/894</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2023/#created-894</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Errors in forming function items&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Follow-up to issue #888&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of situations in which error behaviour is insufficiently specified:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider the partial function application &lt;code&gt;fn:contains(?, 23)&lt;/code&gt;, where the second argument is an integer, not a string. Does the partial application fail, or does it result in a function item that fails when dynamically evaluated? The spec does not say.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider the expression &lt;code&gt;function-lookup(fn:name, 0&lt;/code&gt;) evaluated when there is no context item in the dynamic context. Does the call on function-lookup fail, or does it return a function item that fails when dynamically evaluated? The spec does not say, though there are numerous test cases in the function-lookup test set that suggest the latter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The same is true for the expression &lt;code&gt;fn:name#0&lt;/code&gt; evaluated when there is no context item in the dynamic context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider a user-defined function &lt;code&gt;my:f&lt;/code&gt; with a parameter that has a default value of "."; consider both a function reference &lt;code&gt;my:f#0&lt;/code&gt; and a partial application &lt;code&gt;my:f(?)&lt;/code&gt; evaluated when there is no context item. Again, I think the spec is unclear on the error behaviour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels to me that the right thing to do in all these cases is to raise the error early: that is, to fail at the point where a function item is being constructed, not at the point where the function item is subsequently evaluated. However, this disagrees with QT3 expected test results for tests such as &lt;code&gt;fn-function-lookup-267&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;function-literal-267&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
