<item>
   <title>Issue #954 created</title>
   <pubDate>2024-01-17T00:45:02Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/954</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2024/#created-954</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Establish a default value for the XSLT fixed-namespaces attribute&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The newly-defined &lt;a href="https://qt4cg.org/specifications/xslt-40/Overview.html#fixed-namespaces"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fixed-namespaces&lt;/strong&gt; attribute&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;em&gt;&lt;code&gt;xsl:stylesheet&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; element is a huge positive step towards improving programmer's productivity by removing the need to provide up to 9 namespace declarations in every stylesheet module, thus reducing unnecessary cluttering, simplifying and slimming the code and increasing its readability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like an accidental omission that the current text doesn't specify a default value for this attribute. If there is a well-chosen default value, this would even further decrease the requirements for the programmer to engage in such a non-problem-solving activity as entering memorized strings, and would prevent errors such as either not providing the correct values for the namespace-uris or forgetting to specify this new attribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One obvious candidate for a default value of the &lt;strong&gt;fixed-namespaces&lt;/strong&gt; attribute is &lt;code&gt;#standard&lt;/code&gt;, which means that without having to press even a single additional key, the XSLT programmer gets all standard namespaces automatically bound to the well-known prefixes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;xsl&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;xml&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;xs&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;xsi&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt;  &lt;code&gt;math&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;array&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;err&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Proposal:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please, augment the current text by specifying that the default value for the &lt;strong&gt;fixed-namespaces&lt;/strong&gt; attribute is &lt;code&gt;#standard&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
