<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div1 id="id-conformance">
    <head>Conformance</head>
    
    <changes>
        <change issue="205" PR="326" date="2023-02-01">
           Support for higher-order functions is now a mandatory feature (in 3.1 it was optional).
        </change>
        <change issue="1343" PR="1344" date="2024-09-03">
          The static typing feature has been dropped. 
        </change>
        <change issue="2022" PR="2026" date="2025-05-28" role="xquery">
          The module feature is no longer an optional feature; processing of library modules
          is now required.
        </change>
        <change issue="2602" role="xquery">
          The EXPath binary and file modules are now categorized as optional features.
        </change>
    </changes>

    

    <p>This section defines the conformance criteria for an &language; processor. In this section, the
        following terms are used to indicate the requirement levels defined in <bibref ref="RFC2119"
        />. <termdef id="must" term="must"><term>MUST</term> means that the item is an absolute
            requirement of the specification.</termdef>
        <termdef id="mustnot" term="must not"><term>MUST NOT</term> means that the item is an
            absolute prohibition of the specification.</termdef>
        <termdef id="may" term="may"><term>MAY</term> means that an item is truly
            optional.</termdef>
        <termdef id="should" term="should" role="xquery"><term>SHOULD</term> means that there may exist valid
            reasons in particular circumstances to ignore a particular item, but the full
            implications must be understood and carefully weighed before choosing a different
            course.</termdef>
    </p>


      <p role="xpath">XPath is intended primarily as a component that can be used by
      other specifications. Therefore, XPath relies on specifications that
      use it (such as <bibref ref="XPTR"/> and <bibref ref="xslt-40"/>) to
      specify conformance criteria for XPath in their respective
      environments. Specifications that set conformance criteria for their
      use of XPath <termref def="mustnot">MUST NOT</termref> change the
      syntactic or semantic definitions of XPath as given in this
      specification, except by subsetting and/or compatible extensions.</p>
      
      <p role="xpath">If a language is described as an extension of XPath, 
      then every expression that conforms to the XPath grammar <termref def="must">MUST</termref> 
          behave as described in this specification.
      </p>

      <p role="xquery">An XQuery processor that claims to conform to
      this specification <termref def="must" >MUST</termref> include a
      claim of Minimal Conformance as defined in <specref
      ref="id-minimal-conformance"/>. In addition to a claim of
      Minimal Conformance, it <termref def="may">MAY</termref> claim
      conformance to one or more optional features defined in <specref
      ref="id-conform-optional-features"/>.</p>

      

    <div2 id="id-minimal-conformance" role="xquery">
        <head>Minimal Conformance</head>
        <p>An implementation that claims <term>Minimal Conformance</term> to this specification
                <termref def="must">MUST</termref> provide all of the following items:</p>
        <olist>
            <item>
                <p>An implementation of everything specified in this document except those features
                    specified in <specref ref="id-conform-optional-features"/> to be optional. If an
                    implementation does not provide a given optional feature, it <termref def="must"
                        >MUST</termref> implement any requirements specified in <specref
                        ref="id-conform-optional-features"/> for implementations that do not provide
                    that feature.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>A definition of every item specified to be <termref
                        def="dt-implementation-defined">implementation-defined</termref>, unless
                    that item is part of an optional feature that is not provided by the
                    implementation. A list of <termref def="dt-implementation-defined"
                        >implementation-defined</termref> items can be found in <specref
                        ref="id-impl-defined-items"/>.</p>
                <note>
                    <p>Implementations are not required to define items specified to be <termref
                            def="dt-implementation-dependent"
                        >implementation-dependent</termref>.</p>
                </note>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>An implementation of <bibref ref="xpath-datamodel-40"/>, as specified in <specref
                        ref="id-data-model-conformance"/>, and a definition of every item specified
                    to be <termref def="dt-implementation-defined">implementation-defined</termref>,
                    unless that item is part of an optional feature that is not provided by the
                    implementation.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>An implementation of all functions defined in <bibref ref="xpath-functions-40"/>,
                    and a definition of every item specified to be <termref
                        def="dt-implementation-defined">implementation-defined</termref>, unless
                    that function or item is part of an optional feature that is not provided by the
                    implementation.</p>
            </item>
        </olist>
    </div2>
    <div2 id="id-conform-optional-features" role="xquery">
        <head>Optional Features</head>

        <p>The features discussed in this section are optional. An implementation <termref def="may"
                >MAY</termref> claim conformance to one or more of these features.</p>

        <p>The description of each feature mentions any errors that occur if a query relies on a
            feature that is not present.</p>


        <div3 id="id-schema-aware-feature">
            <head>Schema Aware Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-schema-aware-feature" term="schema aware feature"
                    >The <term>Schema Aware Feature</term> permits the query Prolog to contain a
                        <termref def="dt-schema-import">schema import</termref>, and permits a query
                    to contain a <code>validate</code> expression (see <specref ref="id-validate"
                    />). </termdef>
            </p>

            <p>If an XQuery implementation does not provide the Schema Aware Feature, it <termref
                    def="must">MUST</termref> raise a static error <errorref class="ST" code="0009"
                /> if it encounters a schema import, and it <termref def="must">MUST</termref> raise
                a static error <errorref class="ST" code="0075"/> if it encounters a
                    <code>validate</code> expression.</p>

            <p>If an implementation provides the Schema Aware Feature, it <termref def="must"
                    >MUST</termref> also provide the <specref ref="id-typed-data-feature"/>.</p>
        </div3>


        <div3 id="id-typed-data-feature">
            <head>Typed Data Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-typed-data-feature" term="typed data feature">The
                        <term>Typed Data Feature</term> permits an XDM instance to contain element
                    node types other than <code>xs:untyped</code> and attributes node types other
                    than <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code>.</termdef>
            </p>

            <p>If an XQuery implementation does not provide the Typed Data Feature, it <termref
                    def="must">MUST</termref> guarantee that:</p>

            <olist>
                <item>
                    <p>The XDM has the type <code>xs:untyped</code> for every element node and
                            <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code> for every attribute node, including nodes
                        created by the query.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Elements constructed by the query always have the type
                            <code>xs:untyped</code>; attributes constructed by the query always have
                        the type <code>xs:untypedAtomic</code>. (This is equivalent to using
                            <code>construction mode = strip</code>.)</p>
                </item>
            </olist>
        </div3>

        
        <div3 id="id-serialization-feature">
            <head>Serialization Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-serialization-feature" term="serialization feature">The
                        <term>Serialization Feature</term> provides means for serializing the result
                    of a query as specified in <specref ref="id-serialization"/>.</termdef> A
                conforming XQuery implementation that provides the Serialization Feature <termref
                    def="must">MUST</termref> conform to <specref ref="id-serialization"/>. An
                implementation <termref def="may">MAY</termref> provide other forms of
                serialization, which do not conform to the Serialization Feature, and are beyond the
                scope of this specification. </p>
            <p>The means by which serialization is invoked is <termref
                    def="dt-implementation-defined">implementation-defined</termref>.</p>
            <p>If an error is raised during the serialization process as specified in <bibref
                    ref="xslt-xquery-serialization-40"/>, an implementation <termref def="must"
                    >MUST</termref> report the error to the calling environment.</p>

            <p>An implementation that does not provide the Serialization Feature <termref def="must"
                    >MUST NOT</termref> raise errors when reading an <termref
                    def="dt-output-declaration">output declaration</termref>, and <termref
                    def="must">MUST</termref> implement <code>fn:serialize</code>; it <termref
                    def="may">MAY</termref>, however, raise an error when <code>fn:serialize</code>
                is invoked, as specified in <xspecref spec="FO40" ref="func-serialize"/>. An
                implementation that does not provide the Serialization Feature <termref def="may"
                    >MAY</termref> provide results of a query using a vendor-defined
                serialization.</p>

            <note>
                <p>Some implementations return query results without serialization. For instance, an
                    implementation might provide results via an XML API or a binary representation
                    such as a persistent DOM.</p>
            </note>
        </div3>
        
        <div3 id="id-expath-binary-feature">
            <head>Binary Library Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-binary-library-feature" term="binary library feature">The
                        <term>Binary Library Feature</term> provides a set of functions
                    for manipulating binary data, specifically, atomic values of type
                    <code>xs:base64Binary</code> and <code>xs:hexBinary</code>.</termdef></p>
            
            <p>These functions are defined in <bibref ref="expath-binary-40"/>.</p>
            
            <p>An implementation claiming conformance to this feature <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>:</p>
            
            <olist>
                <item><p>Include these functions in the static context of every query module;</p></item>
                
                <item><p>Include in the static context of each query module a namespace binding of the
                prefix <code>"bin"</code> to the namespace URI <code>http://expath.org/ns/binary</code>
                (subject to the same rules as other predeclared namespace bindings: see 
                <specref ref="id-namespaces-and-qnames"/>);</p></item>

                <item><p>Return <code>true</code> as the result of the expression
                <code>fn:system-properties()?#supports-binary-library</code>.</p></item>
            </olist>
            
            <p>An implementation that does not claim conformance to this feature:</p>
            
            <olist>
                <item><p><rfc2119>May</rfc2119> provide a subset of the functions;</p></item>
                <item><p><rfc2119>May</rfc2119> predeclare the <code>"bin"</code> namespace;</p></item>
                <item><p><rfc2119>Must not</rfc2119> provide any functions in the <code>"bin"</code> namespace
                        that do not conform to the cited specification;</p></item>
                <item><p><rfc2119>Must</rfc2119> return <code>false</code> as the result of the expression
                <code>fn:system-properties()?#supports-binary-library</code>.</p></item>
            </olist>

        </div3>
        
        <div3 id="id-expath-file-feature">
            <head>File Library Feature</head>
            <p>
                <termdef id="dt-file-library-feature" term="file library feature">The
                        <term>File Library Feature</term> provides a set of functions
                    for manipulating files in an external filestore.</termdef></p>
            
            <p>These functions are defined in <bibref ref="expath-file-40"/>.</p>
            
            <p>An implementation claiming conformance to this feature <rfc2119>must</rfc2119>:</p>
            
            <olist>
                <item><p>Include these functions in the static context of every query module;</p></item>
                
                <item><p>Include in the static context of each query module a namespace binding of the
                prefix <code>"file"</code> to the namespace URI <code>http://expath.org/ns/file</code>
                (subject to the same rules as other predeclared namespace bindings: see 
                <specref ref="id-namespaces-and-qnames"/>);</p></item>

                <item><p>Return <code>true</code> as the result of the expression
                <code>fn:system-properties()?#supports-file-library</code>.</p></item>
                
                <item><p>Provide <termref def="dt-implementation-defined"/> mechanisms
                enabling predictable results from the invocation of functions with
                side-effects: see <specref ref="functional-purity"/>.</p></item>
            </olist>
            
            <p>An implementation that does not claim conformance to this feature:</p>
            
            <olist>
                <item><p><rfc2119>May</rfc2119> provide a subset of the functions;</p></item>
                <item><p><rfc2119>May</rfc2119> predeclare the <code>"file"</code> namespace;</p></item>
                <item><p><rfc2119>Must not</rfc2119> provide any functions in the <code>"file"</code> namespace
                        that do not conform to the cited specification;</p></item>
                <item><p><rfc2119>Must</rfc2119> return <code>false</code> as the result of the expression
                <code>fn:system-properties()?#supports-file-library</code>.</p></item>
            </olist>

        </div3>

        

        

    </div2>
    <div2 id="id-data-model-conformance" role="xquery">
        <head>Data Model Conformance</head>
        <p>All XQuery implementations process data represented in the <termref def="dt-datamodel"
                >data model</termref> as specified in <bibref ref="xpath-datamodel-40"/>. The data
            model specification relies on languages such as XQuery to specify conformance criteria
            for the data model in their respective environments, and suggests that the following
            issues should be considered:</p>
        <olist>
            <item>
                <p>
                    <emph>Support for normative construction from an infoset.</emph> An
                    implementation <termref def="may">MAY</termref> choose to claim conformance to
                        <xspecref spec="DM40" ref="const-infoset"/>, which defines a normative way
                    to construct an <termref def="dt-data-model-instance">XDM instance</termref>
                    from an XML document that is merely well-formed or is governed by a DTD.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>
                    <emph>Support for normative construction from a PSVI.</emph> An implementation
                        <termref def="may">MAY</termref> choose to claim conformance to <xspecref
                        spec="DM40" ref="const-psvi"/>, which defines a normative way to construct
                    an <termref def="dt-data-model-instance">XDM instance</termref> from an XML
                    document that is governed by a W3C XML Schema.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
                <p>
                    <emph>Support for versions of XML and XSD.</emph> As stated in <bibref
                        ref="xpath-datamodel-40"/>, the
                    definitions of primitives such as strings, characters, and names 
                    are based on the definitions in XSD 1.1, though operations that require
                    use of an XML Schema processor <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> use an XSD 1.0 processor.
                    If new versions, editions, or errata are published for XML, XSD, or related specifications,
                    then implementations <rfc2119>may</rfc2119> adopt any changes.</p>
                <note>
                    <p>For suggestions on processing XML 1.1 documents with XSD 1.0, see <bibref
                            ref="xml11schema10"/>.</p>
                </note>
            </item>

            <item>
                <p><emph>Ranges of data values.</emph> 
                    Limits are defined in <xspecref spec="DM40" ref="atomic-type-limits"/>.</p>
                
                <note>
                    <p>For discussion of errors due to <termref def="dt-implementation-dependent"
                            >implementation-dependent</termref> limits, see <specref
                            ref="id-kinds-of-errors"/>.</p>
                </note>
            </item>
        </olist>
    </div2>
    <div2 id="id-syntax-extensions" role="xquery">
        <head>Syntax Extensions</head>
        <p>Any syntactic extensions to XQuery are <termref def="dt-implementation-defined"
                >implementation-defined</termref>. The effect of syntactic extensions, including
            their error behavior, is <termref def="dt-implementation-defined"
                >implementation-defined</termref>. Syntactic extensions <termref def="may">MAY</termref> be used without
            restriction to modify the semantics of a XQuery expression.</p>

    </div2>
</div1>
