<item>
   <title>Issue #2476 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-02-19T15:16:57Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2476</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2476</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guaranteed streamability&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The XSLT Streaming specification defines conditions under which a stylesheet is deemed to be "guaranteed streamable": see §3.1 Streaming Guarantees, and requires a streaming processor under these conditions to process the source document in streaming mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specification also states that if the stylesheet is not "guaranteed streamable", but streaming is requested, then the processor must report a static error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter requirement is very burdensome because it requires the streamability analysis to be done without any tree rewrites of the kind that would turn a non-streamable construct into a streamable one. This means, for example, that type inferencing must be done before any rewriting. Saxon attempts to meet the requirement, but there are almost certainly areas where it fails to do so. Saxon is also non-conformant in that the option to check for guaranteed (i.e. interoperable) streamability is off by default. The only benefit of the requirement for users is that they know that if one conformant streaming processor can handle the stylesheet, then every conformant streaming processor will be able to do so. But even if multiple conformant streaming processors were available, this benefit would be minor in proportion to the burden on implementors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I propose dropping this requirement from the spec. It will still be true that a conformant streaming processor must always use streaming if the stylesheet adheres to the rules in the spec; it will no longer be the case that a conformant streaming processor is required to raise an error if it doesn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
