<item>
   <title>Issue #2503 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-03-06T15:34:52Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2503</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2503</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Range constraints in fn:dateTime-record fields&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This follows on from https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2263#issuecomment-3961934656 (by @michaelhkay)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also need to say more about the constructor functions associated with built-in record types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, consider fn:dateTime-record. Does the constructor function for this record type impose any constraints beyond those in the type signature? Does it ensure that month is in the range 1-12? Does it ensure that if month is 4, then day is in the range 1 to 30? Does it ensure that if hours and seconds are present, then minutes is also present?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And editorially, where do we document this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment &lt;a href="https://qt4cg.org/specifications/xpath-functions-40/Overview.html#dateTime-record"&gt;F&amp;amp;O § 9.3 Record fn:dateTime-record&lt;/a&gt; reads as though non-optional range constraints are being specified for most of the fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they're not optional, when are implementations expected to confirm that values conform to their respective field constraints?  When accessed via &lt;code&gt;fn:build-dateTime&lt;/code&gt; the spec says that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dynamic error is raised [&lt;a href="https://qt4cg.org/specifications/xpath-functions-40/Overview.html#ERRFODT0006"&gt;err:FODT0006&lt;/a&gt;] if any of the components in $value is outside the permitted range (for example if the value of the minutes component is less than zero or greater than 59), or if the combination of fields is not a valid date/time (for example, if month is 4 and day is 31).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is an implementation also expected to check the field-specific ranges when a value is retrieved using, for example, &lt;code&gt;?day&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;map:get($my-dateTime-record, 'day')&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, is an implementation expected to validate inputs when the record is initially constructed (via &lt;code&gt;fn:parts-of-dateTime&lt;/code&gt; or the implicit constructor)?  Or, also, each time they're modified, for example, using &lt;code&gt;map:put&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further context, when a user defines a custom record type in XSLT (&lt;code&gt;xsl:record-type&lt;/code&gt;), it doesn't appear possible to specify a range constraint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
