<item>
   <title>Issue #2518 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-03-11T16:13:58Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2518</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2518</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Type Safety&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building on issue #1979, I suggest that we define a limited set of cases where processors are required to report a static type error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain constructs have a readily determined static type, including&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;variable references if the type is declared&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;static function calls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;literals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;most binary operators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The XSLT streaming spec gives a simple set of rules at https://qt4cg.org/specifications/xslt-streaming-40/Overview.html#static-type-of-xpath-expressions - we could adapt these rules easily enough. Those rules were written before choice types were available and could now be simplified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, any operand context that applies function coercion has a required type which we already define.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could define that it is a static error if the static type of an expression has no overlap with the required type, and cannot be coerced to the required type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As suggested in #1979, we could then define that $x?y is a static error if the static type of $x is a record type and y is a field that is not defined in the record type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could also absorb some of the current definition of "implausibilities", for example by making @x/@y a static type error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a backwards compatibility implication: we'll be detecting errors in code that weren't reported statically before, but would only be reported if actually executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't a proposal to reintroduce "strict" or "pessimistic" static typing as defined for XQuery 1.0. It only reports errors for constructs that are provably wrong, whereas 1.0 static typing required the code to be provably correct. Reporting "provably wrong" constructs statically has always  been permitted (and has always been implemented in Saxon); this merely makes it mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
