<item>
   <title>Issue #2521 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-03-12T14:23:25Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2521</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2521</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;File retrieval, URIs: fragment identifiers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fragment identifiers are now allowed in &lt;code&gt;fn:doc&lt;/code&gt; calls, but they are still illegal in other functions (like &lt;code&gt;fn:unparsed-text&lt;/code&gt;), for no apparent reason. We should generally allow them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While reviewing qt4cg/qt4tests#340, I noticed again that the error codes for &lt;code&gt;fn:unparsed-text&lt;/code&gt; are a bit of a mess, and difficult to adhere to when using low-level I/O:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A dynamic error is raised [err:FOUT1170] if the $source argument contains a fragment identifier, or if it cannot be resolved to an absolute URI (for example, because the base-URI property in the static context is absent), or if it cannot be used to retrieve the string representation of a resource.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A dynamic error is raised [err:FOUT1190] if the value of the encoding option is not a valid encoding name, if the processor does not support the specified encoding, if the string representation of the retrieved resource contains octets that cannot be decoded into Unicode characters using the specified encoding, or if any resulting character is not a permitted character.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A dynamic error is raised [err:FOUT1200] if the encoding option is absent and the processor cannot infer the encoding using external information and the actual encoding is not UTF-8.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things don’t get better with the introduction of the fallback option. I would prefer to see them merged to single error code, preferably &lt;code&gt;FOUT1170&lt;/code&gt;, and to simplify the description to…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dynamic error is raised [err:FOUT1170] if the the string representation of a resource cannot be retrieved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…or to at least drop FOUT1200 and merge it with FOUT1190.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
