<item>
   <title>Issue #2592 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-04-23T10:39:01Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2592</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2592</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;fn:parse-json: parsing numbers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With 4.0, &lt;code&gt;fn:parse-json&lt;/code&gt; has been equipped with a &lt;code&gt;number-parser&lt;/code&gt; option. It works fine if you know your data in advance. User feedback indicates that it fails to deliver a convenient solution for arbitrary input. In addition, it requires a configuration which allows you to specify function items as options (which is tricky, for example, for command-line options).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would we take a big risk by making the interpretation of numbers more flexible? We could adopt the rule for &lt;a href="https://qt4cg.org/specifications/xpath-functions-40/Overview.html#element-and-attribute-content"&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn:element-to-plan&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the prescribed type is numeric and the value is castable as &lt;code&gt;xs:numeric&lt;/code&gt;, then it is output as an instance of &lt;code&gt;xs:integer&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;xs:decimal&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;xs:double&lt;/code&gt; depending on the lexical form of the value, following the same rules as for XPath numeric literals. For example, &lt;code&gt;"-1"&lt;/code&gt; becomes an &lt;code&gt;xs:integer&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;12.00&lt;/code&gt; becomes an &lt;code&gt;xs:decimal&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;1e-3&lt;/code&gt; becomes an &lt;code&gt;xs:double&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would see many advantages; among other:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obvious integer input could be handled as such without further conversions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will have fewer losses in roundtripping scenarios with large numbers and many decimal places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debugging with the adaptive serialization method would become handier (without changing it, see #2389):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-xquery"&gt;(: current result: 1.0e1 :) 
declare option output:method 'adaptive';
parse-json('10')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this change, I assume that &lt;code&gt;number-parser&lt;/code&gt; option can be avoided in most cases, and I cannot think of big trouble that the introduced backward-incompatibility could cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
