<item>
   <title>Issue #2613 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-05-03T07:17:29Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2613</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2613</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;XSLT: result of xsl:array-member&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;xsl:array-member&lt;/code&gt; returns a "parcelled" value that is subsequently used by xsl:array to form a mamber of an array. The parcelled value is currently represented as a zero-arity function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I propose to change this so the result is represented as a JNode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disadvantage of the current approach is that the representation used by xsl:array-member doesn't correspond to the representation used by any of the standard mechanisms used for decomposing an array into its members. So it's fine for constructing a brand-new array, but not for operations like adding or removing members to an existing array. This makes it hard to find a good way of transforming arrays using template rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this change, we would be able to do something like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;xsl:variable name="$array" select="parse-json($cities)/*"/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;xsl:variable name="$subarray" as="array(map(*))&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;xsl:array&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;xsl:sequence select="$array[?country='UK']"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;xsl:array-member select="{'name': 'Douglas', 'country': 'Isle of Man'}"/&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;/xsl:array&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/xsl:variable&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to construct an array that combines members selected from an existing array with newly constructed members,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic changes are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;xsl:array-member returns a parentless JNode that encapsulates the selected value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;xsl:array takes a sequence of items. Each item becomes one member of the array. If the item is a JNode, it is unwrapped to use its &lt;code&gt;jvalue&lt;/code&gt; property. The &lt;code&gt;jkey&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;jparent&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;jposition&lt;/code&gt; properties are ignored.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This then raises the question of whether we should do the same for &lt;code&gt;xsl:map&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;xsl:map-entry&lt;/code&gt;. Symmetry suggests we should. But there are a couple of complications: firstly, we have to think about backwards compatibility, since xsl:map-entry is present in XSLT 3.0. Secondly, the JNode produced by xsl:map-entry would have a key but no parent, which is a novelty in terms of the current data model, and we would need to reassure ourselves that this has no unintended consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
