<item>
   <title>Issue #2681 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-06-10T15:35:15Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2681</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2681</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Refine specification of map-for-key() in XSLT&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;map-for-key() was introduced by PR #1622.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the second argument of map-for-key() is optional, it should allow an empty sequence for consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current spec does not define the order of entries in the resulting map. It should specify that the order is implementation-dependent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the third paragraph of the Errors section, the reference to the &lt;code&gt;key&lt;/code&gt; function should be a reference to &lt;code&gt;map-to-key&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spec says: &lt;em&gt;The returned map contains one entry (K, V) for every atomic item K where the result of key($key-name, K, $top) is not empty, with V set to the result of key($key-name, K, $top).&lt;/em&gt; But there can be an infinite number of items that satisfy this condition, for example, QNames with different prefixes. We should only return one key for each "equality group" in the underlying index. That's a slightly slippery concept, but essentially we should return the entries with distinct keys, on a suitable definition of "distinct".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underlying this is a slight implementation difficulty: the spec for &lt;code&gt;xsl:key&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;key()&lt;/code&gt; function does not actually require us to hold the "real" key for an entry, in the sense of the result of the &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; expression. We can instead hold some kind of internal "collation key" used for matching. It's not always possible to reconstruct the original atomic value from the collation key. In most cases (given that we require the key to use codepoint collation) we can construct an equivalent key, and I think that's all that the spec should require. For example, this means we aren't required to deliver the original type annotation, the original timezone, or with QNames, the original prefix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we can say something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let UU be the set of atomic items U for which the result of key($key-name, U, $top) is not empty, and let KK be the result of eliminating duplicates from UU according to the rules of the atomic-equal function. (Note, the set UU is potentially infinite: for example in the case of QNames, there is an infinite set of prefixes that can be chosen for a QName. The set KK, however, is always finite, and contains one value for each set of equivalent values obtained by evaluating the &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; expression in the key definition. The particular choice of atomic item from the set of candidate values is implementation-dependent; for example, with QNames, the item chosen might be one that has no prefix. The chosen key is not necessarily one that actually arose from evaluation of the &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; expression: for example, it might have the type annotation xs:string when all the original keys were instances of xs:untypedAtomic.) Then for each atomic item K in the set KK, the returned map contains an entry (K, V) where V is the reuslt of &lt;code&gt;fn:key($key-name, K, $top)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
