<item>
   <title>Issue #2695 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-06-19T13:24:52Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2695</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2695</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;XSLT: apply-templates with maps, arrays, and JNodes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are three parts to the challenge of making template rules work effectively for transforming JSON-derived trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part is designing match patterns that work effectively. We have largely achieved this with PR2678, though I think there is still work to do on matching records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This second part is concerned with the apply-templates instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final part, which I think can be tackled independently, is to define the effect of the built-in default template rules, especially those for mode="shallow-copy".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For apply-templates with a select expression, I propose no change, if only because the semantics are already defined in XSLT 3.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the absence of a select expression, the current rule is that it's an error if the context item is not a node (XNode). I think we can do better than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the context item is an atomic item, we should apply templates to that atomic item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the context item is a JNode, we should apply templates to the children of the JNode; and if the context item is a map or array, we should wrap the map or array in a JNode and apply templates to its children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's then a question, if you're processing a map or an array, whether the results of apply-templates should be used to construct a new map or array, or whether (as now) they should be left as a sequence. I'm inclined to say that if you want an array or map, you construct it yourself, so you write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;xsl:array&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;xsl:apply-templates/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/xsl:array&amp;gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;xsl:map&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;xsl:apply-templates/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/xsl:map&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It becomes the responsibility of the author of the template rules to return values that are suitable for use in constructing an array or a map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
