<item>
   <title>Issue #2733 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-06-26T17:22:03Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2733</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2733</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A step too far: path expressions involving JNodes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's really great to be able to write expressions like &lt;code&gt;booklist/book[author='Mike']/price&lt;/code&gt; but there are usability traps. Consider this test case:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;test-case name="K2-Steps-40"&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;description&amp;gt; 
         RHS of "/" operator can be any PostfixExpr. 
         LHS of dynamic function call is coerced from JNode to function(*)* 
      &amp;lt;/description&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;created by="Michael Kay" on="2026-04-24"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;dependency type="spec" value="XP40+ XQ40+"/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;test&amp;gt;{"A":1, "B":{"C":3, "D":4}}/B/.("C")&amp;lt;/test&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;result&amp;gt;
         &amp;lt;assert-eq&amp;gt;3&amp;lt;/assert-eq&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/result&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;/test-case&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The test is wrong: can you see why? The answer is that it successfully evaluates the final step &lt;code&gt;.("C")&lt;/code&gt; to obtain the value 3, but it doesn't return 3 as the final result of the expression, rather it computes &lt;code&gt;{"A":1, "B":{"C":3, "D":4}}/B/3&lt;/code&gt; which returns nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm coming to the view that this isn't acceptable. The semantics of G/A where G evaluates to a GNode and A evaluates to an atomic value are wildly different depending on whether G is an XNode or a JNode, and this is going to cause no end of confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A possible solution is to allow the current semantics only in the case where the step is an NCName or a literal. If it's anthing else, for example a variable reference, you have to write &lt;code&gt;G/child::{$i}&lt;/code&gt;. If A is any expression other than an NCName or a literal, then G/A works with JNodes the same as it does with XNodes - the "/" operator is essentially treated as "!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're still breaking referential transparency; writing 23 has a different effect from using a variable whose value is 23. That's essentially because "/" was never a pure operator in the first place, there have always been surprises in its semantics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
