<item>
   <title>Issue #2742 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-07-01T08:58:28Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2742</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2742</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;JNode identity: closer alignment with XML node identity?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A JNode wraps a map or array as the root of a JTree if &lt;code&gt;fn:jtree&lt;/code&gt; is called, or if a path is traversed. &lt;code&gt;fn:jtree&lt;/code&gt; currently says that it “typically returns a new JNode with its own identity”, but “may” return the same JNode for repeated calls on the same input; the behavior for queries like &lt;code&gt;(1 to 3) ! {} ! jtree()&lt;/code&gt; (which may be rewritten to &lt;code&gt;replicate({}, 3) ! jtree()&lt;/code&gt;) is left to the implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheer length of the rules and notes for &lt;code&gt;fn:jtree&lt;/code&gt; indicates that it is prone to unexpected system behavior (something I already experienced multiple times now during development). For instance, the behavior of the example given for &lt;code&gt;fn:distinct-ordered-nodes&lt;/code&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-xquery"&gt;let $x := [ 1, "a", true() ]
return count(distinct-ordered-nodes(
  ($x/*[1], $x/jnode(*, xs:integer)) 
))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…is currently implementation-defined (and needs to be dropped or changed if we keep the current rule set for &lt;code&gt;fn:jtree&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have already discussed this before, but my impression is that the current state is not satisfying enough to keep it. Maybe we should think about strengthening the rule so that &lt;strong&gt;every&lt;/strong&gt; explicit/implicit construction of a root JNode yields a JNode with a distinct identity. The advantages I see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Same model as for XML:&lt;/strong&gt; XDM gives every constructed node a fresh identity, and processors already preserve this under optimization. Reusing the same rule would allow us to reuse much more existing XNode properties and optimizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identity independent of value:&lt;/strong&gt; JNode identity depends on the map/array’s weakly-defined value identity. Tying it to the construction instead means value optimizations (sharing, folding, etc.) could never change a result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simplicity:&lt;/strong&gt; I would assume that simpler rules automatically improve the consistence of implementations and (at least in the long term) makes it easier for users to understand what’s going on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arising challenge will be how to tackle the increased nondeterminism of ·jtree· and the path expression, but it’s something that is at least known from functions like ·fn:parse-xml·.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
