<item>
   <title>Issue #2758 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-07-03T22:46:09Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2758</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2758</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;XSLT: Visibility of item types and record types across packages&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;xsl:item-type&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;xsl:record-type&lt;/code&gt; declarations have a visibility attribute defining whether they are local to a package or can be accessed from using packages. They are also included in the types of component that can be named in &lt;code&gt;xsl:expose&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;xsl:accept&lt;/code&gt;. But other details have not been followed through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are not included in the definition of "component" in §3.4.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because item types cannot be overridden in a using package (for good reasons), much of the discussion of component binding in §3.4.5 does not apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact it's debatable whether named types should fall within the definition of "components" at all; they certainly don't need to inherit all the complexity. However, they probably do need to be within the scope of &lt;code&gt;xsl:expose&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;xsl:accept&lt;/code&gt;, which gives them some of the properties of components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any constructor functión associated with a named record type has the same visibility as the record type; it can't be overridden in a using package. This needs to be stated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In §3.4.7, the paragraph starting "Type names used in the interface of public components...." definitely needs revision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not directly relevant to this issue, but the final para of §3.4.7 "At execution time, the schema available for validating instance documents contains (at least) the union of the schema components imported into all constituent packages of the stylesheet." also needs revision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
