<item>
   <title>Pull request #2759 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-07-04T12:11:33Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/pull/2759</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2759</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;1506 Type declarations: Constructor functions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;[NEW] This PR originally introduced constructor functions for type declarations, restricted to enums and atomic types (see below). As it turned out, the feature already existed in the spec (which also explains the existing test case).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My confusion was caused by the fact that we closed #1506 without further notice, and that this was not mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;Item Type Declarations&lt;/em&gt; section. Next, its note claims that item type names never need to be retained at execution time, which contradicts the constructor functions. The PR tries to complete the picture, without changing the scope of the feature:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The section on item type declarations points to the existing constructor function rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Annotations rules/arity overlap have been added, they seemed to be missing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A note has been corrected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;→ And we definitely need more test cases (indicated, for now, with the »Tests Needed« label). I will do my best soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[OLD] This PR introduces constructor functions for type declarations – a feature for which, surprisingly, we already have a test case, &lt;a href="https://github.com/qt4cg/qt4tests/blob/c0183a06487621e5f218b2e44f69acd02b39a8a4/prod/ItemTypeDecl.xml#L381-L394"&gt;itemTypeDecl-026&lt;/a&gt;… (we certainly need more)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to restrict the creation of constructor functions to declarations of enums and atomic types, for the following reasons mainly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We avoid different semantics for &lt;code&gt;record&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;type ... as record&lt;/code&gt; declarations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functions (incl. maps &amp;amp; arrays) can’t be built from a value; it would basically be a simulation of &lt;code&gt;instance of&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;treat as&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unions and choices are non-trivial: for &lt;code&gt;declare type n as (xs:double | xs:decimal)&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;n(1.5)&lt;/code&gt; the result depends on the order in which the type was written, which is easy to get wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
