<item>
   <title>Issue #2786 created</title>
   <pubDate>2026-07-13T15:14:58Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2786</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2026/#created-2786</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clarify interoperability of fragment identifiers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The current specs take the position that fragment identifiers are implementation defined:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of a fragment identifier in the supplied URI is &lt;a href="https://qt4cg.org/specifications/xpath-functions-40/Overview.html#implementation-defined"&gt;implementation-defined&lt;/a&gt;. One possible interpretation is to treat the fragment identifier as an ID attribute value, and to return a document node having the element with the selected ID value as its only child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is an interoperability problem. Ignoring, or failing to correctly interpret, a fragment identifier can have a profound impact on the document processed. If the processor silently ignores fragment identifiers, I may get wildly incorrect results. In a workflow involving many documents or large documents, or both, this could be difficult to catch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it would be better to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fragment identifier schemes supported by a processor are implementation-defined. (So, technically, implementations must enumerate the schemes they support.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processors must report an error if they encounter a fragment identifier that uses a scheme that they do not recognize or cannot cannot be processed (because of implementation limits, or syntactic errors in the scheme, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementations &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; support the xmlns and element schemes for XML documents and RFC 5147 for text resources. Obviously, they may support other schemes as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
