<item>
   <title>Pull request #143 created</title>
   <pubDate>2022-09-15T16:51:59Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/pull/143</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2022/#created-143</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure updates&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This PR doesn't make any technical changes (and it probably won't build correctly as a PR, so I'm just going to merge it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I tinkered a little bit with the URIs on the specifications so that they point to more accurate URIs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've tried to make a few of the XSLT files "less chatty". I'd like to make it easier to see what the errors and warnings are so that we can resolve them. It's the sort of thing that bugs me, so if no one else does it, I'll probably chip away at them as we go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I reworked the way that the XPath Functions and XSLT specifications are built. I've pulled the tasks out of the ant files and implemented them directly in Gradle. (The XPath and XQuery specifications are as yet unchanged, they're more complicated and this already took longer than I had anticipated.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;specification/{specid}/build&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;specification/{specid}/html&lt;/code&gt; directories are no longer used. All of the build and intermediate files are under &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt;. (For XPath Functions and XSLT.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I stopped trying to build all the namespace documents. Those aren't useful unless they're installed in the "real" URIs and I have no idea if/how we'll be able to update those. When we're closer to the end, I can get the namespace documents building again. For now, it's just faster not to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's now easier to see what is happening and Gradle will do a better job of managing the dependencies. So if you are building it locally, it should do less work on each build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything should just build the same way it used to. Changes to the sources or the stylesheets should cause the right builds to run. It is, of course, possible that I've broken something. I tried to check everything, but there are a lot of moving pieces here. Comments, questions, and complaints most welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
