<item>
   <title>Issue #159 created</title>
   <pubDate>2022-09-27T18:13:03Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/159</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2022/#created-159</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Support named arguments on static function calls&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This proposal adds the ability to specify the names (referred to here as "keywords") of the parameters of a function at the point at which the function is called. This uses the form &lt;code&gt;name: value&lt;/code&gt; where name is a QName and value is a single expression, for example &lt;code&gt;fn:tokenize("abcbdCef", pattern: "c", flags: "i")&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a function takes several arguments of the same type (xs:boolean, xs:integer, xs:string, etc.) it can be easy to mix up the parameters. As such, it can be useful to specify these by name when calling the function, e.g. &lt;code&gt;f(a: true(), b: false(), c: true())&lt;/code&gt; to both aid readability and to prevent bugs when the values are specified in the wrong order to how they are declared (such as swapping the &lt;code&gt;$pattern&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$flags&lt;/code&gt; parameters in &lt;code&gt;fn:tokenize&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a function takes several optional parameters and the caller only wants to override one of the later parameters (such as the &lt;code&gt;$collation&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;fn:differences&lt;/code&gt;), specifying the name of the parameter avoids specifying a value for the other arguments. This makes it clearer what is happening (as the user does not need to think about the supplied default arguments), and reduces errors (such as specifying a wrong default value for the arguments the caller is not interested in).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because function parameter names are EQNames, the keyword should also be an EQName. If the keyword is an NCName, then it should follow the same rules as parameter NCNames such that the namespace URI is empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like with maps, if the value starts with an element name (EQName) then there must be a space after the &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt;. This should use the same note as the one in the map constructor section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An alternative &lt;code&gt;name := value&lt;/code&gt; syntax has also been suggested. An informal consensus is in favour of using &lt;code&gt;name: value&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
