<item>
   <title>Pull request #1888 created</title>
   <pubDate>2025-03-20T04:57:46Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/pull/1888</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2025/#created-1888</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;366 xsl:package-location&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First draft, for initial feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because the CG has little energy/resources to develop the EXPath Zip module, I have situated the question of archive (compressed or not) in the URI scheme itself. There are dozens of archives, dozens of URI schemes. The only case where I have found overlap is in the &lt;code&gt;jar:&lt;/code&gt; scheme/archive. Yes, I've seen &lt;code&gt;zip:&lt;/code&gt; used as an alias for &lt;code&gt;jar:&lt;/code&gt;, but it's not an official IANA URI scheme. This may need discussion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have opted to bind &lt;code&gt;@priority&lt;/code&gt; to a non-zero integer. This is the first time the constraint for the union of positive and negative integers has been placed on an XSLT attribute, so I may not have correctly set up &lt;code&gt;element-catalog.xml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have opted to not make attribute values &lt;code&gt;format&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;version&lt;/code&gt; as criteria for the priority package location (new term), so that developers can be warned when the package is at odds with the declaration. To make them criteria would mean that inconsistencies between the declaration and the referenced packages would remain undetected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I adopted the terms "URL" and "entry" based upon the IANA nomenclature for the jar: scheme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I may have overthought the distinction between archive and non-archive URIs. Feedback is appreciated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Error code &lt;code&gt;3000&lt;/code&gt; has been broken up into different possible errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suggestions on the type and number of tests that need to be written for the test suite are welcome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
