<item>
   <title>Issue #1951 created</title>
   <pubDate>2025-04-23T15:54:00Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/1951</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2025/#created-1951</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some nits regarding the method attribute&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few minor comments on the method attribute (that also apply to XSLT 3.0):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A note in section 25.1 says "In the case of the attributes &lt;strong&gt;method&lt;/strong&gt;, cdata-section-elements, suppress-indentation, and use-character-maps, the effective value of the attribute contains a space-separated &lt;strong&gt;list&lt;/strong&gt; of EQNames."  The effective value of the method attribute should not be a list of values, just one value, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The XSD schema requires that the method attribute contain a colon if it is not one of the 6 "built-in" values.  (The type xsl:method restricts xsl:EQName with the pattern "\c*:\c*").  Now that it can be an expanded QName,  it should also allow for Q{...}.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A note in section 3.2 says:  "Extension attributes may also be used to influence the behavior of the serialization methods &lt;strong&gt;xml, xhtml, html, or text&lt;/strong&gt;, to the extent that... If a serialization method other than one of these &lt;strong&gt;four&lt;/strong&gt; is requested (&lt;strong&gt;using a prefixed QName&lt;/strong&gt; in the method parameter) then...".&lt;br/&gt;
a. This lists only 4 methods, Should "json" and "adaptive" be added to the list and "four" changed to "six"?
b. Should "using a prefixed QName" be changed to something like "using an EQName with a non-absent namespace"?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the note about error XTSE1570 in Section 26.2.  "The value must (if present) be a valid EQName. If it is a lexical QName with no a prefix, then it identifies a method specified in [XSLT and XQuery Serialization] and must be one of &lt;strong&gt;xml, html, xhtml, or text&lt;/strong&gt;.
a. It only lists the 4 methods, leaving out "json" and "adaptive"
b. Typo - "no a prefix" should be "no prefix"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
