<item>
   <title>Pull request #1990 created</title>
   <pubDate>2025-05-08T18:22:50Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/pull/1990</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2025/#created-1990</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Update schema-for-xslt40.xsd&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fixed invalid syntax xs:simpleType/@ref (moved to @memberTypes) in simpleType named method&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based the type fixed-namespaces-type-default on xs:token instead of xs:string to allow for whitespace normalization&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changed collation attribute on xsl:merge-key to be an avt (according to spec)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changed attributes that were previously of type "xsl:char-optionally-expanded" to just xs:string since the spec says they can be any string.  I couldn't think of a reason they should be limited to one character optionally followed by a colon and more characters, so I assumed this was some sort of artifact from the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changed xsl:next-iteration and xsl:evaluate to not allow mixed content&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corrected _split_when to _split-when&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Added missing shadow attributes (in two places) for allow-duplicate-names, build-tree, json-lines and json-node-output-method&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Added missing shadow attribute for select on perform-sort&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Added assertions for required attributes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;xsl:use-package - name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;xsl:expose - names, component and visibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Made the errors attribute a list of tokens instead of just xs:token.  Doesn't affect validation but I think it is more clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changed default value of per-mille from a tilde to ‰&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changed the default value of the on-no-match attribute from shallow-skip to text-only-copy, per the spec&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gave xsl:exclude-result-prefixes the same type as no-namespace exclude-result-prefixes, to allow for #all and #default&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gave xsl:extension-element-prefixes the same type as no-namespace extension-element-prefixes, to allow for #default&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removed the xsl:prefixes and xsl:char-optionally-expanded types since they were no longer used after the above changes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changed the type of the visibility attribute on xsl:attribute-set, xsl:function, xsl:template and xsl:variable to xsl:visibility-not-hidden-type to exclude "hidden" per the spec&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changed the keyword value of the fixed-namespaces attribute from #default to #standard (and adjusted type names)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
