<item>
   <title>Issue #2325 created</title>
   <pubDate>2025-12-01T11:13:45Z</pubDate>
   <link>https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2325</link>
   <guid>https://qt4cg.org/@qt4cg/2025/#created-2325</guid>
   <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Specify evaluation more tight and more formal to disallow unsane cases&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="markup"&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's very hard to change the spec to disallow over-optimization of a construct like &lt;code&gt;if ($x &amp;gt; 0) then "positive" else error()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could you please clarify which over-optimization do you mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically a processor can determine when it starts evaluating this expression that the only possible outcome is either the string "positive" or an error, and it can therefore return "positive" immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We just have to assume that no sane implementor is going to do that. I can't see an easy way to change the rules to mandate this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted by @michaelhkay in &lt;a href="https://github.com/qt4cg/qtspecs/issues/2314#issuecomment-3595888452"&gt;#2314&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is about the rule from 2.5.4 &lt;a href="https://qt4cg.org/specifications/xquery-40/xpath-40.html#id-errors-and-opt"&gt;Errors and Optimization&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if [...] there are only two possible outcomes of evaluating &lt;em&gt;Q&lt;/em&gt;, namely the value &lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt; or an error, then the processor may deliver the result &lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt; without evaluating further items in the operand &lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a filtering expression &lt;code&gt;E[ P ]&lt;/code&gt;, this rule allows to filter out those items in &lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt;, examining of which raises an error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are negative consequences if  the rules are changed so an error during obtaining an item from &lt;em&gt;E&lt;/em&gt; cannot be ignored, but an error during examining an item in &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; may be interpreted as false() (i.e., the item may be filtered out) ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
</item>
